<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
  <title>CPU cores</title>

  <para>Several CPU cores have been adapted to the MaSoCist build
  environment.</para>

  <section>
    <title>ZPU small core 'Zealot'</title>

    <para>The Zealot core is a non-pipelined CPU, designed by Salvador E.
    Tropea, based on the 'ZPU small' design by Øyvind Harboe. It is enhanced
    by a In Circuit Emulation module (proprietary in house standard "StdTAP")
    for native JTAG debugging on FPGA hardware. The HDL for this CPU is
    OpenSource.</para>

    <para>This CPU variant is a full 32 bit CPU, not allowing unaligned
    access, therefore uses 32 bit addressing on a 4 byte for I/O access only.
    It is also enhanced by a small WishBone wrapper to access externally
    supplied IP cores (I2C, UART). The Zealot core has limited possibilities
    for customization.</para>

    <para>The ZPU interrupts are non-reentrant, i.e. only one interrupt
    service at a time is processed.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>ZPUng core</title>

    <para>The ZPUng ('ng' standing for 'next generation') core is a pipelined
    proprietary redesign of the original ZPU architecture in the Python HDL
    extension <application>MyHDL</application>. A short overview:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Instruction compatible to the ZPU small, big endian</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Three stage pipeline with shortcut mechanisms for some
        instruction sequences</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Separate Stack and Data/Program memory</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Typical native instruction duration: 1 cycle (up to 3 cycles on
        I/O and ALU operations)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Enhanced interrupt, exception and event vector capabilities
        (ZPUng v1)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Extended StdTAP debugging features</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Slightly higher logic usage than ZPU small</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Easily configureable and extendable using custom microcode
        extensions (ZPUng v2)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The ZPUng code is primarely available in VHDL under a custom source
    license. Verilog output can be supported on request.</para>

    <para>The ZPUng v1 minimum configuration typically synthesizes in less
    than 800 LUTs (including debug logic), depending on architecture.</para>

    <para>The ZPUng v2 is still under development and offers higher speed,
    however it breaks compatibility to ZPUng v1 with respect to microcode
    emulation features. Also it can be configured to use a different opcode
    set. Custom operations can be implemented such that some processing is
    occuring in parallel, but still within a calleable function, accessible to
    an application programmer. The main ZPU machine code is still compatible
    to the classic ZPU variants. Interrupt and debugging functionality on the
    ZPUng v2 are yet limited.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>PyPS core</title>

    <para>The PyPS core is based on a classic MIPS architecture design with a
    few specific optimizations with regards to Block RAM. It runs up to 70 MHz
    on Spartan3 platforms ('cordula' configuration) with a BRAM register bank.
    Higher speeds can be achieved with distributed register RAM.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>MIPS-I instruction set with microcode enhancements
        (DIV/MUL)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Five-Stage pipeline with hazard resolving unit</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>StdTAP debugging interface</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Limited MIPS16 ASE option (no exception support)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Configureable to be either fully compatible to MIPS-I or
        fast</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Limited interrupt support (use DMA where possible)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DMA coprocessor option (two simultaneous memory channels)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note>
      <para>The PyPS core is no longer maintained for new designs due to its
      complexity and resource usage. It is recommended to use the ZPUng v1.1
      instead.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
</section>
